Hi, welcome back! In the previous video I explained you
你们好，欢迎回来！ 在之前的视频里我向你们解释了
because you want to be warned if a certain value
因为当你把两张工作表连在一起的情况下，
isn't found when integrating two worksheets. However, there are scenarios,
你想收到当查找结果未能发现时的有关警告信息 但是，在某些情况下，
is the good choice, and in this video I will explain you when
是不错的选择，而在这个视频我 将会为你们解释
you have to use TRUE. So, for instance, when we're doing this analysis:
什么时候你必须使用TRUE。 举例来说， 当我们做以下的分析时：
in this new worksheet I've created, we're going to have a detailed look
在这张我创建的新的工作表里， 我们将会有详细地解释
into the use of margins. So, for instance, you had to
如何计算利润率。 譬如你要与你的销售总监会面
talk with your sales director and he said "Hey, I would like to know
他说：“我想了解一下，
for what product we have a good margin and for what other products our margin
我们哪些产品的利润率比较高，
could be
而哪些产品的利润率
increased maybe?". So, first of all,
有待提高？” 那么首先，
for each code we're going to look up the margin. And this is still just
我们将为各个商品代号查看其利润率。 而这一步仅仅只是
an old fashioned VLOOKUP with the FALSE,
使用了传统的VLOOKUP加上FALSE的功能，
where we're going to the ProductInfo and we're returning the sixth column,
我们现在先查看ProductInfo，并返回第六列，
which is the margin. We change that.
即利润率。 我们来更改它。
Again, don't forget the dollar sign, it's really important that you remember that!
再次提醒，不要忘了货币符号，这点十分重要！
And then you drag the formula down and you have all the margins.
之后你把公式往下拖，就可以得出所有的利润了。
Now we want to do the analysis on top of it. So we want to know
接下来，我们在这一步的基础上再进行分析。 现在我们想了解一下
is this a good margin or a bad margin. We can input
某个利润率究竟是理想还是不理想。 我们可以为此输入一条公式，
a formula for that, a simple conditional formula that we talked about in
那是一条简单的条件公式，
previous videos.
就像我们在之前的视频介绍过的一样。
We just say: if our margin is, let's say,
如果我们的利润率，譬如说，
smaller than 20 percent then it's bad. In the alternative case, if it's bigger than
小于20％，那么它是不理想的。 如果它大于20％，
20 percent, but still smaller than 30,
但仍小于30%，
we're going to say the margin is OK, and in other cases, if it's above 30,
我们就说这个利润率还过得去， 而如果利润率在30%以上，
then we're going to say: yes, our margin on this product is good!
那么我们会说这款产品的利润率十分理想。
So, yes, we can do this with a conditional formula,
的确，我们可以用 条件公式 来做到这一点，
just drag the formula down,
只需将公式拉下来
and we have it! Nothing wrong with it,
就行了 这种方法没有什么不对，可是
well, we are nesting conditions here and you should remember from previous videos
我们在这里嵌套了好几个不同的条件。还记得以前的视频提到过的吗？
complicated.
过于复杂。
You might not expect it, but this is actually a very good scenario
很多人可能不会想到，这 种情况
to use a VLOOKUP! It is really different from
其实我们可以好好利用VLOOKUP这个功能。 它跟之前我们说过的查找多张工作表中的
looking up values over two tables, but actually
某个数值不大一样，但VLOOKUP的确可以
the VLOOKUP applies here, and let me show you how! What we can do here
在这里派上用场，请留意我接下来是怎么做的。 我们在这里要做的是
is add a table in our worksheet where we add the classification.
在添加工作表分类的地方，再加入一个表格。
So we say: for margin of everything above
我们来设定：
zero the classification is going to be bad,
利润率小于零为不理想的，
is going to be OK, and everything above 20, between 20 and 30,
而高于20，即是20到30之间，
is going to be good. The exact same classification as we just put into
则是理想的。 这个分类正是与我们输入
the conditional formula. Now we can
条件公式 时是一样的。 现在，我们就可以
get rid of the whole IF, the nested IF that we didn't really like,
去掉整个IF语句了， 因为我们并不喜欢这个镶嵌的IF语句，
and put a VLOOKUP there. We're going to look for
然后把VLOOKUP放进那里。 我们要找出
the value of the margin in this new
在这个新的利润率表格里，利润率的数值是多少
margin table, we're returning the second column
让我们回到第二 列
and then we're going to add TRUE, because we don't want to look for 22,
然后把TRUE加上去， 我们并不能查找“22”，
you know that 22 is not in the table. We want to look
因为"22"并不在在表中。 我们只想
for the closest margin that there is, to 22.
找出最接近22的利润率。
And you see that the functionality in this VLOOKUP
看到了吧，这时VLOOKUP的功能
is exactly the same as the functionality of the IF.
是与IF的功能完全一样的。
And doing it this way you can see it's very easy, because if you want to change
这种方法其实是十分简单的，因为如果你想改变
something in my table you just saw me change
表格里的一个数值，像你刚才看到的
'ok' into uppercase 'OK'. I can just do that
我把ok改为大写的OK。 我可以直接在
in the table, I don't need to change the formulas, just change my table
表格里改，并不需要改变 公式，
and all the formulas are updated. Even more so,
一但我在表格里改变某个内容，所有的公式会被立即更新。 不仅如此，
if I want to add another classification, like 40 percent is
如果我想添加其他的分类， 例如我想把40％
Whereas if I should I do that with an IF, then I would have gone on
反之，如果我用的是IF，我就要另外
another branch of the IF and my formula would get longer and longer and longer.
为IF添加另一个分支命令，那么我的公式就变得越来越长了，
And with this VLOOKUP solution it doesn't matter how many classifications
而有了这个VLOOKUP，无论有多少分类
I have. If I have a hundred, this formula will still be one
都不要紧。 如果我有一百个分类，这个公式 依然只有一个
VLOOKUP, whereas if I have a hundred classifications
VLOOKUP，可是如果我
in a conditional formula, then I'll have a hundred IF.
用的是条件公式 ，那么我的公式里将会有一百个IF。
Or, actually, I would have ninety-nine IFs, but that would still be a lot.
其实严格来说只有99个IF，但是这仍然是太多了。
So, if you are classifying things, if you are dividing a certain value
所以说，当你要进行分类，即是当你要把一个数值
into different categories using an IF,
用IF语句来分成不同类别
then I hope you remember this scenario - you could use VLOOKUP
那么我希望大家记住这点：
with TRUE
你可以使用填入TRUE作为参数的VLOOKUP
to substantially simplify your formulas in such scenario.
来大幅度简化公式。